Wizards just updated a
card type that's almost
10 years old, and it significantly
affects every
format in the game.
Let's talk about the
rules update for
Sagas in the Final Fantasy set.
Judging by the
Final Fantasy release notes, Wizards
are going to change
two Saga rules.
Rule 714.3 B and
rule 714.4.  Let's start with
rule 714.4.  And
we'll come back to the other change later.
Rule 714.4 states
that when a Saga has
lore counters
equal to or
greater than the number of
its chapters, and this is not a
result of a
chapter ability, the controller of
that Saga sacrifices it
as an action
based on
game state.  This rule was
most often
used in
Modern, where players
had to
sacrifice their Urza's
Saga when Blood Moon was in play
.  The saga became a
mountain and lost all
chapter abilities, which
means their
number is
zero.  According to
rule 714.2 D and
current rule 714.4
, Saga should have been
sacrificed.  This
decision was also
important for
future Saga creatures (
summons) from the Final Fantasy set.
If such a creature were
in play and its
chapter ability was
cancelled by Tashana's Tidebinder
, its text was
replaced by Deadpool , or
it was hit by
Humility , you
would have to
sacrifice that
creature, as it would
lose all
chapter abilities again.
So what's happening
with the rules update?
At the time of writing, I
only have the
Final Fantasy release notes, so there
is no official wording of the rules yet.  However, the
article states that
the change will be that
if Saga doesn't
have
chapter abilities, she won't
be subject to the effect
that requires her
to be sacrificed due to
the number of
knowledge counters.
Additionally, Sagas will now
only gain knowledge counters after the draw step
if they
have
chapter abilities.  If they
don't have any
sections, nothing will
happen.  The two
biggest impacts:
Saga creatures will no longer
be instantly
sacrificed by
Tashana's Tidebinder, Deadpool, or the
Humility effect.  And
most importantly—Blood Moon
is no longer a tough
counter to Urza's Saga.  What's
more, now it might
make Saga even
better.  Under the new
rules,
playing Blood Moon will
simply turn
Urza's Saga into a mountain and it
will not be sacrificed.
Additionally, if you
had Urza's Saga in play with
two
lore counters, it would have
the ability to give
colorless mana and
the ability to pay
to create a
construct token.  And even
if the opponent
played Blood Moon, Urza's
Saga would retain these two
abilities.  Not
only that: since
Urza's Saga has no
chapter abilities, she will
no longer
gain
knowledge tokens each turn,
meaning she can
stay on the board for
multiple turns,
creating
construct tokens for just
two mana.  And it's all
thanks to one thing—
layers.  Let's
take this step by
step and go through it in
order.  First,
if we look
at the abilities of the
Urza Saga chapters, we
see: this saga
gets "turn:
add one
colorless mana" and "
turn, pay
two mana: create
construct."  These two
effects are examples of
continuous
6th layer effects that add
or remove
abilities.  These
abilities are not
innate to the
saga itself, unlike
some creatures from Final
Fantasy who have
abilities like
flight or haste.
They are added as
part of a
continuous effect
created by the
triggered
ability of the saga itself.
The easiest way
to compare this is to a
card like Chance of Glory,
which says your
creatures gain
invulnerability.  You will
notice that this
effect has no
time limit.
Once the
spell is cast, this effect
becomes continuous and
applies to
creatures you already
have on the
field.  The same thing
happens with
Saga
Urza's abilities.  They
trigger, after
which the continuous
effect is permanently
applied to the
saga.  If we
look at Blood Moon,
we see an
ability that
turns non-base
lands into mountains.  This
is applied on the
4th layer of type change effects
.  Lands that have become
mountains effectively
lose all the
abilities
printed in
their text.  This is the
most important part
.  According to rule
305.7, if an effect
sets a
land's subtype as one or
more base types,
that land no longer
has its old
type.  It loses
all abilities from the
rules text, old
land types, and any
copy effects that
affected it.  And it
gets the corresponding
mana-giving ability for each
new basic
land type.  Note that this
does not remove abilities
granted to the land by other
effects.  So,
let's look at what
happens when we
have Blood Moon on the field and
two
knowledge tokens on Urza's Saga.  We have
three continuous
effects to
apply.
Converting all
non-basic lands into
mountains, giving
Urza's Sage a mana ability,
and granting her
the ability to create
constructs.  We
apply them in
the order of the layer list.
Starting at layer 4,
Urza becomes a mountain and
loses all of his
rules text.  Then
we move to
layer 6 and apply the
mana ability and
then the
construct ability to our "
saga mountain" in
chronological
order.  I know this
will elicit a lot of
comments along the lines of: "
That makes no sense at all
."  Well,
welcome to the world of layers.
They are not always
intuitive
, but that is how
the rules of the game work now.
Here is one example
that may help
understand this better.
Let's say you have a
new land in the game, the
Golden Plate, which
has certain abilities.
Then
Blood Moon is played,
followed by Eternal Horror.  Will the
Golden Plate be
invulnerable?
Most of you
will say yes, since
we apply the layers
in the same order
.  We change the type of the
Golden Plate to "
Mountain", and it loses
all its printed
abilities.  Then we
apply Eternal
Terror on the sixth layer and
she gains
invulnerability.  The
same thing happens with
Urza's Saga and
Bloodmoon, but
instead of spells
granting abilities, it
was a triggered
chapter ability.
OK.  So, if the
Blood Moon
no longer stops the
Urza Saga, what
can we do?  In addition to
destroying the land, we
need to affect
Urza's Saga on the
sixth layer and
remove all of her
abilities there.  There
are currently four cards that
can do this.
Blood Sun,
Alpine Moon,
Lithiform Plague, and a
new map from Final Fantasy—
Ultima: Dawn of
Oblivion.  All four
cards contain the
keywords "
loses all
abilities".  Let's
take a look at one of
these effects in action,
as they all
work in pretty much the
same way.  Situation
one: There is an Urza Saga in the game
with two
knowledge counters.
You are playing
Bloody Sun.  If
we go to Layers
, we have three
continuous effects
that we want to
apply on the
sixth layer.  And if
you've watched my
previous videos about
layers, you know that
according to rule 613.7,
we apply them in
order of
timestamp,
oldest to
newest.  So, we
first
apply the
mana ability,
then the
construct ability, and then the
Blood
Sun ability, which causes
Urza's Saga to lose all of
its abilities.  This
means that
Urza's Saga will lose its
construct ability
and its
chapter abilities.  So while
she will no longer
gain
knowledge counters,
she will not be able
to create
constructs.  Situation
two: we have
Blood Sun in the game, and our
opponent plays
Saga of Urza.  This
time, Urza's Saga
will come into play, and nothing will
happen because she
has no abilities.
She won't even
get the first
knowledge counter, so
she won't even have the
first chapter mana.
As I mentioned, the
other three cards work
pretty much the same way.  Although
for Ultima and the
Lithiform Sea,
only the
first situation is relevant here.  It's
also worth noting that in the
first situation,
Alpine Moon
will remove
Urza's Saga mana ability and
replace it with "
return, add
one mana of any
color."  Again
, this is similar to Litho
form Blight and Ultima.  So, this is a
rule change that
comes with the release of the
Final Fantasy set.  What do you
think about this?  As
always, if you
learned something new,
don't forget to
like the video.
Let me know in
the comments below
if you have any other
questions, and
subscribe or
I'll tell Wizards
to make Blood Moon 2.
Thanks for watching,
see you in the
next video.